hello everybody
thanks for tuning in i hope you're uh
i hope the life that you find yourself
living is um how shall we say it
that you're as you come to terms with it
you're finding
that there are no terms that quite can
say it such
that you keep thinking to yourself i
wish
should be a word for that and that
those words that you make up in
describing your life
are ones in which you would want to
you would want to use ungoingly so i
hope you're doing well
um i wanted to read
over this paper that i have been writing
which is
going to be a chapter into it
in an anthology with um
chris and john verbaki and i think
jordan hall
and a lot of the people that i've been
talking to on my channel
and the book is going to be called inner
and outer dialogues
and so i've been working on this for the
last number of months as you've probably
heard me talk about
um and it's it's it's interesting
because
i've never really written anything kind
of academic
or at least academic and like this so
this is my first
adventure to doing so and i'm finding it
to be incredibly immersive in a really
cool way
um and having something
having something that because i'm always
thinking about stuff
right i'm always wondering about things
and contemplating things and meditating
on things and
you know cultivate as much as i can
or find myself in a state of wonder
about what's happening and what is
reality
what is being it just seems to me that
whatever that
wonder bug is um has been
its valve is is really open and there's
something about
having this writing project
has been a um a very close feedback week
for that
so it's kind of i had this experience of
almost like everything i'm doing
is running through the frame of this
paper so uh
i'm just about done with that but i
wanted just to read
read through it um just to see how it
all comes together
and um notice places that aren't quite
fluent
or that i want to change or um as i'm
reading it so thank you for tuning in
and this is just the rough draft of
of the paper and uh what i'll do is i'll
i'll just read through it and i'll
probably stop at certain points and
extrapolate and maybe do it a little bit
like
like you see in these kind of academic
conferences where they
you know somebody gives a talk and then
they read and then they
they talk about what they just read and
then they go on reading something like
that so
okay so
i'm gonna read it here for my computer
and here's the introductory part
in this chapter i attempt to look
through thea the logos
and not just hear logos but rather
following heraclitus listen to logos
through listening show logos as
precisely what is nearest
and at the same time and by virtue
of its nearness is simultaneously
the most remote and hidden from us
it is precisely the history of this
deafening to logos that characterizes
the nihilism of our modern epoch
in which heidegger calls the age
of technology
following heidegger's reading of
holdren's poem
quote where the greatest danger
so too is the saving power
unquote i will propose
precisely the moment we hear that we are
not listening
is the same moment listening to logos
has begun in other words
if you're looking at the emergence in
the culture of what john verveigh has
termed
psychotechnologies and hearing what
these practices
are responding to can be a way of
hearing
the gathering of the logos from out
of its own concealment and perhaps
giving us a hint in how to listen
and in so do it attune
to logos discontingent
sustaining source
it is in this spirit that i will look
to the social relational practice of
circling
that since its spontaneous emergence
1998 has organically spread throughout
the world
to be a revelation of
and a response to the loss
of logos specifically
the loss as the missing sense
of meaningful interpersonal connection
and community rapidly disappearing
in our time i will attempt to show
during an in
an in-depth examination of the way
circling is practiced
to be a disclosure of the logos
through enacted philia
making way for philia sophia
and the possibility of dialogues
so if you're not familiar philia is the
um it's considered
i mean the most simple translation is
it's
it's the love of friendship right and in
the deepest sense in the way that i'm
meaning it's it's that
it's the friendship that you
it's the i thou love the way of being
that's not
it's a love that's not a possession but
a friend
in the deepest sense of the word that
it's your
there's a sense in which you want you
find yourself just
wanting them to exist um
on for its own sake so
by leah
i go on i will first lay the groundwork
by inquiring into the meaning of the
word logos
through examining the etymology of key
terms
targeting back to heraclitus and ancient
greece
this will show the primacy of logos as
the dynamic
ground of intelligibility enabling
access
to the world as such this will allow us
to appreciate the profundity
and implications of the loss of logos
making way for understanding of
heidegger's notion
of the history of being
through stretching out heidegger's
astonishing insight into the history of
metaphysics
as the forgetfulness of being and the
basis
of nihilism and the technological
instrumentalizing
dominance of our current epoch
this will lay this will lay the ground
to zero in on a specific structural
change technology is made on the medium
of social discourse
here i will look at social discourse
as a mode of logos this will reveal
sociality
in a profoundly different light than
traditionally understood by the social
sciences
rather than sociality being a region of
our world
as a result of our social activity
instead
when understood as logos the world
is precisely what enables our social
relations
the speech of social discourse becomes
the way the logos
weaves the intelligibility of the world
as such
understanding the social as an
ontological dimension
of being as such lets us see
what has always been at stake in our
social relations
is the world itself this understanding
allows us to attune to the historical
unfolding of the world
and hear the logo speak from
out of its anonymity addressing
our conscience as a call to
authentically
being with
this will also allow us to appreciate
the depth
of what is at stake in dialogue
as a site for world closure
and disclosure
with this context we examine the
emergence
of circling in full breadth of the logos
and the possibility it opens
to hear the original voice of heraclitus
from the future as the possibility
of theologists okay so that's the
introduction
okay the first section here is called
logos and meaning
all right to the degree
the world the world and my love
sorry to the degree the world and my
life
is felt as intrinsically meaningful
is to the degree to which the particular
situation
of my being in the world is sense to be
connected to what is greater
and beyond me particular people
places and events in my life glow
with a sense of moreness calling me
beyond the current
shape my current shape thereby
shaping the world that shapes
me weaving the articulation
of the togetherness already whole
conversely when
conversely when my being in the world
loses
its intrinsic sense of meaningfulness
the particular such situation of my life
becomes what i am standing
over and against having to deal with it
the dealing of of which is contingent
upon my effort of production
of producing an outcome which is the
next contingency
i stand over and against this process as
such
itself already always
being the outcome itself contingent on
the previous
generation of production
the world becomes the standing
means reserved for extraction
and optimization of further production
martin heidegger in his thinking in his
thinking the metaphysics of the west
saw i should turn that off sorry about
that do not disturb
okay sorry about technical difficulties
martin heidegger in his thinking the
metaphysics of the west
saw the nihilism it necessitated
as the quote forgetfulness of
the being of beings unquote
in other words when the non-contingent
wholeness of being is not heard
beings do not disclose the sense of
moreness
but rather derive their meaning in terms
of their utility
function and contingency
logos gathers what all
beings have in common and in their
togetherness
as beings in other words
the gathering of being into beings
is the logos my aim in discussing the
logos
is less explanatory as initiatory
initiating in this in the same way the
logos
through heraclitus initiated the origin
of the western thinking of being
and thus the originating source of all
thinking sense by source
i do not mean something that is earlier
than everything else
but rather
by source i'm going to say that again by
source i do not mean something
that is earlier than everything else but
rather
comes as the earliness itself
the logos as originally spoken by
heraclitus
is the non-contingent sustaining
principle
and source gathering the togetherness of
the unity
of being into intelligibility
logos is the ontological gathering
to self-arising thatness
that's an ancient greek word which
basically means to gather it
the the self arising thatness and
the wetness aussia
of being as such that presupposes
and sustains a unity enabling them to be
grasped
as being historically
the logos was meant has meant word
speech reason order gathering
logic order and even divine word and
divine reason
what these words have in common is they
all speak
of intelligibility they are words that
express the principle at work when
something
is intelligible and thus understandable
webster defines intelli defines
intelligible
as capable of being understood or
comprehended
the words etymology comes from the
inter meaning between plus um
legere which means choose
pick out read um in the the root of that
is leg or liege
which means to to gather
to collect and to gather in other words
something is intelligible by virtue of
it gathering into standing out
able to be understood or grasped legere
from within enter itself as itself
what is the itself that gathers into
itself
making it intelligible in other words
what accounts for the intelligibility of
intelligibility
this is spoken in the root it hasn't
common with logos
leg leech i don't know which one it is
lead your leg
the original gathering that gathers
something
to stand out from itself as itself
is logos logos
is the way the world gathers into
manifestation
yet logos is itself
not a thing that appears
rather logos is the way the
whole of being speaks through the
particular situation
of beings logos withdrawals
in letting the world appear
resonating with the sense of the
inexhaustible
as such
this paradoxical this paradox
of logos disclosure via its concealment
as being is perhaps
is perhaps what accounts well wait a
minute let me read that over again
the paradox of logos disclosure
via its concealment as beings
is perhaps what accounts
accounts it being like accounts
being viewed holistically as the
mysterious and enigmatic
it is also what makes it possible to
become deaf to logos so in other words i
have to rewrite that paragraph
but basically there's what i'm trying to
get at there is there's a way
in which on one level logos
allows things to appear as the things
that they are
right allows me and the light
and ideas and thought and
everything that's intelligible to to
to reveal themselves and stand out as
understandable and
intelligible yet logos itself never
appears as a thing right so i'm trying
to get at that
so there's a way in which it's very uh
it's very openness it's very it's it's
the way that it reveals on some sense
all that is
right is also the way it conceals itself
and so that may account for its enigma
right and how we can
possibly not hear it and i can write a
paragraph that doesn't make any sense
about it
okay so this is uh i go into a uh
a fragment by heraclitus this is a
fragment 50.
and the translation that i use here is
quote provided you listen
not to me but gather yourself
parentheses psyche gather yourself
psyche
into the gathering itself logos and
accordance and gathering gives rise to
the fitting
knowledge one atones
all unquote
to my understanding what this fragment
speaks to
is the key to understanding the hydarian
sense of being and specifically
how being can be listened to
as a way we live in
and participate in beings non-contingent
disclosure
it can also show how we can become
forgetful
of being and thus beings
are revealed in only their contingency
and utility
listening to the logos heraclitus says
is not listening to me
this disclosure this discloses
that it is possible to hear the logos
without listening to it
this i propose sheds light on nihilism
as the forgetfulness of being as well
as revealing an insight into the logos
role in addressing it
when we only hear the speaker but not
the logos his analogies is is an analogy
to only hearing
only hearing beings and not the being of
beings
so there's a there's this parallel where
you know how
um to explain this a little bit so
heidegger's
if you if you're familiar with heidegger
he's constantly you know
um talking about this ontological
difference that that
that this western sense right and it's
really this really only came about and i
think heraclitus and the pre-socratics
were the first ones to conceptualize
this
it was like a big bang of
intelligibility
um that that defines everything that we
call
anything at all from our perspective
right we're living in
what opened up which is
the the sense in which the being
of all beings that which all
beings are grounded in and arise out of
and fall back into
right being you could say with a big b
that that ontological difference
so that's what i'm referring to and
trying to get at with this is that the
logos is the one that kind of
gathers that you know what you could say
gathers the intelligibility
of the being of beings right and without
logos
right it's things are still intelligible
right they're still
you can still understand them you can
still make sense of them
but um but they don't reveal the sense
of moreness
their weirdness their luminosity
right they can shine through them when
being as such is disclosed and that
listening to logos
is though i believe is the key to that
shining forth
right okay so i'm gonna read that
this fragment reveals its depth only
if we understand the logos is not simply
already
quote in the one
if this were the case the all
would already be atoned to the one and
we could simply passively
hear it instead it takes a
quote fitting knowledge
what is this fitting knowledge
fittedness
refers to continuity of belonging
together in what way
does the human being belong together
with logos
to the ancient greeks and explicitly
articulated by
hair by aristotle what
makes the human being distinct from all
other beings
is its logos more specifically
the human being lives in speech in every
way
speech being another word for logos
the human being is born into a world
structured by language and thus
becomes the being they are in and
through
speech as heidegger says in a lecture
course
on on aristotle he puts it
quote here's the quote speech
is the being and becoming of humans
themselves
unquote speech is the being and becoming
of
humans themselves so you can see this
very very tight relationship
i go on in other words human beings are
the beings
they are in their fundamental
constitutional
openness to logos
fitting knowledge therefore is
synonymous with the human beings
coming to full realization their
possibility
of being therefore
listening to the logos as heraclitus's
suggestion is the same process
for our human being in the world to
realize the world through being with
others
in full authenticity as the one
atoning all it's kind of a complex
paragraph i'll
read it again fitting knowledge
is synonymous with the human beings
coming to full realization
i'm sorry to coming to fully realize
their possibility being
therefore listening to the logos as
heraclitus is suggesting
is the same process for our human
being in the world to realize the world
through being with other others in full
authenticity
as the one atoning all so in other words
what i'm saying is that
in order to hear the logos right to
gather yourself into the gathering
itself
in as the one tones all
right this revelation of the moreness
in the suchness of the particular that
that the logos can gather us
that are listening to that given that we
are a being
that has logos right that
that that realization is also you can't
separate it from the realization of the
human being as such
so the realization of being and the
realization
in what it takes to realize being is
exactly what it takes to realize
ourselves
right in our potentiality for being as
such okay
yet implied in our gathering i'm
going on here yet implied in our
gathering
into the gathering itself is that it is
not
simply given
it is given as an ontological potential
of being however if not taken up with
authentic participation
one is destined to fall into mere
hearing authentic listening
is something one undergoes with one's
whole
being as a realization
of our openness as an enacted
unity with the logos which
actualizes the one atoning
all or as heidegger may say
the disclosure of the being of beings
is the clearing of da dassain the
science authentic potentiality for being
and just a note that sign is heidegger's
word basically for
the being of human beings
heraclitus is also giving us a hint
to what happens when we do not listen
and merely hear
just hearing the speaker is synonymous
with inauthentic being in the world
where the one does not atone all
this is the world of what heidegger
would call average
everydayness as inauthentic
being in the world this
is a mere hearing only the surface
of appearances as the way things are
quote unquote and living unquestionable
unquestionably in the given world
you already always find yourself in
you're still living in speech logos
however in an unminding way
where you simply do what one does
because this is what one has always done
in some sense you live within the
measure of the logos
yet being profoundly asleep to the
uncanny fact
that you really exist and you really are
going to die
you respond to the to
you respond to the all of beings
however the contingent source
of being's intelligibility goes
unrecognized by you
and thus the one isn't even
missed and not taken
in into your concern
with the all as such
as heidegger points out inauthentic
being in the world is simply part of
human life
and was so for the ancient greeks
however
the history of the understanding as the
history of the understanding of being
moved out of the greeks
into modernity in terms of metaphysics
has made human life increasingly less
likely
for authentic hearing the sound of logos
which we will explore more later in this
chapter
yet the conditions for the possibility
that such a listening to logos
is also the very same conditions
that make locos likely not heard here's
that paradox again right
again heraclitus gives us a hint here's
fragment 54.
and here's the fragment a harmony that
refrains from
appearing is more vigorous
than one that strives to
and attains an appearance so i'll read
that again
fragment 54 hair clays a
harmony that refrains from
appearing is more vigorous
than one that strives to and attains
an appearance
the logos in this non-appearing
harmony attests to
the original greek sense of truth
as alepha as the happening
of or unconcealment
or as evo degenero translates as
disabscondedness
that sense of truth is marked by the
difference between
a made totality and a whole
of beings which can ring
through appearance yet itself not appear
the harmony is disabsconded
precisely in its non-appearings
in its non-appearance between the notes
gathering the togetherness of the song
in its cosmic harmonia
that's another i declare in the word
harmonia
it is the gathering that the being
of beings can be heard provided
we let ourselves be gap ourselves be
gather be gathering into the gathering
itself
by listening to the harmony of the whole
can atone the world as the present
situation
emily dickinson exemplifies in this poem
and this is her poem
by homely gifts and hindered words
the human heart is told nothing
is the force that renovates the world
yet here is the difficulty in
i'll read that again
by homely gifts and hindered words the
human heart is told
nothing is the force
that renovates the world yet
here is the difficulty in
the renovation the renovation banks
on being able to hear the logos in an
age where it's truth cannot reveal
the concealment as such it's precisely
this sense of the nothing which becomes
flagrant through its non-appearing
gathering logos which the
psychotechnology
circling i will show to be a response to
the loss of
in the culture and a new beginning
via logos as discourse
so basically what i'm trying to get it
there is is you know
this is really complicated on one level
it's really simple but it's very
difficult to bring into
into words but the the original sense of
truth
right the primordial sense of truth al
althea
really is not correctness which
correctness banks on
object idea correlate we call that truth
right correspondence the greek original
sense of the truth was
was that no that that
that that all the good stuff
was in the nothing per se it was in
concealment
and so all atheists to the degree that
that
that truth whatever's true um is the
event of its being revealed
right so for example in the modern sense
of truth
if something it shows up false we call
it
incorrect like in in and that's banked
on that
that's banking on basically an idea
of that um that that the nothing
is nothing it's nil whereas
the further back in history ago right
especially in greece
they would call something um that wasn't
that was false uh being pseudo
the word pseudo right meaning
meaning the truth of it is um is lacking
in appearance
right it's lacking in disclosure but you
can still
see that there's this this presence of a
kind of a pregnant sense of nothing
right so nothing isn't denialism right
it's a
it's a fullness it's it's it's it's par
it's it's part of being right
okay so long have you been going here
i'll go for a little bit longer here a
few more a few more paragraphs
okay the next section metaphysics and
the loss of logos
an in-depth study of heidegger's quote
history
of metaphysics unquote is
far outside the scope of this chapter
and and
is much still debated among scholar
which i am definitely not
a scholar over what heidegger
meant by history however
my understanding of heidegger's thinking
of history provides
a profound way of understanding the time
and context that circling emerged
out of and is a direct response to
it also serves as a pointer back to the
beginning of philosophy
in the ancient socratic practice of
dialogues
which this book is about bringing it
back into the modern context
for heidegger what he calls the history
of metaphysics starts with heraclitus
and the pre-socratic philosophers as the
quote first beginning and inception
of philosophical thinking and
was the first time that the being of
beings
was thought in other words
until the pre-socratics thinking
had not conceived of being as a
whole by virtue of which gave beings
their grounded being this could only
have happened by virtue
of thought of thinking
in other words with the pre-socratics
the most abstract concept
the category of categories and the
context of context
was able to come into view
the onset of thinking being
the onset of thinking being made it
possible
for man to partake in an understanding
that for the first time afforded him
to take a stand in relation
to the world of beings
thinking in language no longer just gave
man holding and shelter in a
mytho-poetic world
but for the first time thinking
gave him the power to take up
the world as such
with this ontological big bang
was the inception of an intelligibility
that we all stand on today making
everything we call
modern and quote self-evident
in the beginning as exemplified in
heraclitus
thinking and being reunified and thought
they were thought together with logos
however as time went on thinking and
being became more and more distinct from
each other
as the separation increased it
it gave us a greater power over the
world
however also an alien ages
alienated us from the world
this combination of external increasing
power
and inner alienation
exemplified thinking's unity
with being as a parasitic processing
where the increased alienation led
to the hunger for more power and control
leading to more alienation this
self-making
estrangement has taken on a life of its
own
culminating in a pernacious taking over
of tech name as the dominant
mode of revealing the world
the being of beings is understood as a
standard the being of beings today is
understood
as a standing reserve
as as our own resource to be optimized
through increasing instrumental
instrument
instrumentalization in a way that
organizes almost everything we do and
are
with every change in ontological
understanding
so too the world itself changed in every
way
as a heidegger saw it this understanding
of being
went through five major epochs
the first onset came with the
pre-socratics
in in which being was understood as
fuses
out of a sense of astonishment or a mood
of astonishment
in that there is being
the second epoch came with the
platonic philosophers in which being
was understood as aussia revealing the
what
being is as the good
and is where knowledge became
a way of revealing the third
epoch came with christianity in which
being became understood as as
monotheistic creator god and beings
as the created
the fourth major epoch
of um ebok of modernity started with
descartes
in which being was understood as
subjects
standing over and against objects
and then then with nietzsche came the
onset
of postmodernism in which being was
understood
as the meaningless upsurging of the will
to power
and the eternal return of the same
through repetitive technical calculation
understood by heidegger as standing
reserve
the very thinking that revealed
the primordial unity of thinking and
being
was the same openness
that made it possible to close in
forgetfulness
of this wholeness and unity with being
this forgetful this forgetful
estrangement of man
from being became first articulated by
descartes
on and the onset of modernity
and i'm going to quote johannes's
teacher um
evo uh evo giannazo i think is his last
name
i'm going to quote him it says the
constellation changes
radically when the revealed truth
christianity ceases to hold sway as a
world
shaping power this novelty in fact marks
the onset
of the modern age or the new times
in the beginning of the modern age or
more modernity
or more modernly man himself
in the newly found freedom of his powers
is required to step in in order to fill
the resulting
gap with his thinking and thus
establishing self as a new ground
for the being as such
and in whole henceforth
men's thinking and not in fact alethea
born
in the in the consonant thinking is the
element in which the ground of being is
constituted
so basically he's you know in quoting
um and quoting him you know it's
basically saying it's
like the christianity was an interesting
period right because
with with the onset of the greeks you
have this really radically different pro
i mean
it's hard to describe how how huge this
was
this sense of being able to some in some
sense grab hold of
being as such right
was the made way for an understanding
for the first time
we have human beings were able to have
an understanding
such that that understanding
upon which revealed the world
differently based on how you understood
it right
that's a huge thing um and that came
out of more mythopoetic thinking which
is
more of man man's speech and language
and thought was more
in terms of finding shelter in beings
right like finding shelter in the
mythopoetic world
so when when
when christianity took hold right it's
really it's a really interesting
thing because it's where these two come
together in some sense right there's
this revealed
uh the reveal truth of christianity
right of the creator god
right and the rationality
right of this
of this more um explicit kind of
thinking
however rationality was used to disclose
the truth already laid out by god right
so you have
a lot of those you know the the way
those um
philosophical doctrines of the of the
middle ages are these kind of rational
proofs
for what god said right and so the
measure of how you knew
it was rational how it was true is to
the degree that you could
explain and reveal what was already
known
right in a certain sense and that's so
man was the creature of god
and rationality was in service of that
right so this is kind of interesting
thing that lasted you know for a long
time and so descartes comes in
and he's in some sense in some sense
he actually deeply fulfilled
christianity
right because christianity had this
really willed to truth that wanted to
reveal the truth
of the revelation of god right and in
some sense
eventually as i think
nietzsche you know pointed out that this
this will to truth
eventually had god
as the creator as the as being
essentially
um to be questioned
right and when that happened right was
was this point where
um was the point of the modern era right
of subject standing over against the
objects
and then basically man in some sense
man's thinking became the measure
right through doubt
of the truth of being okay
i'm just gonna i'm gonna do a couple
more paragraphs and then i think we're
gonna
i'll pick this up another time
it goes on with modernity the separation
of thinking and being
fully explicit in descartes world
shaping actually oh
i think i'm just gonna stop there
with modernity the separation
of thinking and being
became fully explicit in the cart
world in descartes world shaping tweet
i think therefore i am
however in such a way that thinking
has the power of determining the truth
of being being is now contingent on
man's thinking
to represent beings ground to represent
beings grounding in being in other words
beings now need to be grounded in in our
ability to represent them as being
i.e our thinking
no longer was the world laid out as
constituted by it by the non-contingent
revealed truth of a god
and man his rational creature whose
rational powers were were
given to reveal the truth of his creator
now descartes was the car was to carry
out christian christianity's will to
truth
reaching its inevitable destiny to
question the divine
source of this truth and the modern
and and the modern individual and
and eventually led to the question of
god god's world word
itself i'm sorry like this let's
need to rework this paragraph it
eventually led to the question
of the questioning of god
god's word words itself
as subject over against objects
exemplified itself in full articulation
as the industrial revolution that swept
over the entire globe
with being now as an inert
extension of his subjectivity
every part of life rapidly took
on the character of mechanation
everything in the world showed up
is now i'm sorry everything in the world
was now
up for grabs as an object for a
free willing measuring subject
to be clear by the history of the
understanding of
being heidegger didn't mean a mental or
or conscious cognitive activity
but rather history as
the how being unfolds is temporality
specifically in the west by
understanding
he meant what we dwell in
organizing our very sense of the world
an epoch's understanding of being is
what they already always
find themselves being in
as the way the world simply discloses
itself
the understanding of being is the way
the world
already always shows up as given
in the pre-henshin we
find ourselves in the midst of already
coping with
in other words our understanding of
being is the background that withdrawals
in the very
way we inhabit our body our gestures
how we see sense and respond to the
world
prior to conscious reflection it's the
basis upon which we build
our architecture organize our social
roles
and our whole style of dwelling in in
our lived
practices of thinking speaking
and communicating and commuting
it is the basis upon which we conceive
and construct our world
and and those constructions hold
and in turn construct us
our understanding of being in other
words
is precisely what we do not see and
conceive
but rather see with
in this sense our understanding of being
is that which is most concealed
in its nearness and thus is
constitutionally
the farthest away and thus the most
determinant the current postmodern epoch
we are living which we are living
the age of technology
which be is is where being is no longer
primarily intelligible as subjects and
objects
but rather as what heidegger calls the
standing
reserve as revealed through
gestel which is often translated as a
framing
this shift from the modern to the
postmodern
is the transformation from man as
subject overcoming object via mechanism
or will to power into the total
takeover of subjectivism as
standing reserve via technique
or will to will so will the power
like what nietzsche talks about get
transforms into will to will
this understanding of being
in this understanding of being all
beings are intelligible by virtue
of being disclosed as a standing reserve
and the contingent means for production
use and optimization the important
thing to understand with castell is its
is its totalizing leveling of literally
everything including the human being a
standing reserve
so that's the thing about gestel right
so
okay your understanding of being i mean
if you think about it's like
it's the understanding upon which the
background understanding upon which
everything is intelligible in the way
that it's intelligible
right therefore if you change that
background understanding of course it's
going to change
everything else how things show up
like in how they show up and what what
they are
right and so castell is things
are no longer subjects and objects
but now in gestel things are standing
reserved including
the human being so everything is
you know and i'll go on to articulate
this
by techne heidegger was not referring to
technological
objects but rather technique
as the dominant mode of revealing
the world in other words with technic
everything shows up as a resource to be
optimized for
further technological advancement for
the sake
of greater technological advancement
have you ever wondered why why we
they keep making faster phones
like they're faster than the speed of
light or something now
um that's kind of that sensibility
being is no longer understood as the
contingent
one atoning all as a constant
as a constituting wholeness
but instead as a mere totality of stuff
to be ordered into units of calculable
order thus beings
are now apprehended not as objects
within essence but as as
quantified data on call for
exploitation through instrumental reason
the key point here is that everything is
revealed as standing reserve
and um quantified
totality including the human being
both the highest view theo
and the innermost view anto
onto theology basically reveals the
world
as cat as a calculable resource
for its unquestioned advancement
originally in ancient greece techne
named the human activity of making
the activity of techne was seen as
bringing
bringing a being's talos or end
forth into appearance aristotle
conceived that both natural beings and
human in man-made beings had
talos kayla the talos of natural beings
would unfold naturally if unobstructed
for example a seeds talos is a full
grown tree
and if the natural conditions were right
the seed
would would fully unfold as a tree into
appearance
the talos of man-made things on the
other hand
would unfold through the maker's
technical mastery
just as it just as a trees talos
was present but concealed
as a seed from its origins
so too the talos of man-made objects
was present but concealed as idea
and techne was the means by which the
maker
unfolded its being into full appearance
brought it about
every part of the technical
procedure of making was conceived
as a gathering its being from
out of concealment into alepha or truth
the light of appearance the
being of the object was accomplished
through the means of technical mastery
of the maker the greek
understanding of being as the
non-contingent
source or principle of the idea
of the good afforded and sustained
technique
to be the means to gather being
into its light of appearance
i.e being made
in a real sense the meaning and
intelligibility
was already always intrinsically
implicit and technique was
its accomplishing into the truth of its
appearance
every movement of technique was
sustained by a meaningfulness
that was in in a real sense already
there and thus
nurtured into its truth and sustaining
light of appearance
however techne becomes something
drastically different in the post-modern
epoch
epochal understanding of being in
in gestel
as stated earlier in ancient greece
technique was
a human activity and a means of
nurturing forth to
talos of non-contingent being
techne in the post-modern ebok is not
a human activity but rather the
ontological determination
demanding forth of beings as such
in other words technique as a mode of
revealing
is the means by which the totality of
beings
is revealed as the standing reserve
as a standing reserve the standing
reserve in turn
is the means for techniques advancement
which advances by means of revealing
revealing more standing reserve and
so on in an exponential quickening
of the will to will to will
the will to will in the full realization
and coming together of the will to power
as that which is the eternal return
of the same because
technological understanding because the
technological understanding
of the being of beings is no longer
understood as the principle of
principles discontingent source of
intelligibility
disclosing the world as meaningful
presence
but instead in this epoch the being of
the world
is as beings complete withdrawal
from sense and thus the world is
challenged
forth as quantified calculated
contingency
what is uncanny and striking about
technique
as the only mode of revealing is it
cannot reveal itself
as a mode of revealing
is heidegger states technique is
itself is nothing technological
in other words castel as the essence
of modern technology is a mode
of existence that is blind to the
primordial sense of
phusis or thatness
and threatens to be the final mode of
historical
self-concealment of the being of being
as such
heidegger states gestel
is a quote from him quote gestel
conceals
that revealing which in the sense of
poesis lets what
presences come forth into appearance
i'll read that again
castell conceals that revealing
which in the sense of poesis lets
what presences come forth into pure
into appearance where the danger
so to the saving power wrote heiderlin
i propose the saving grace
in our technological age is precisely in
its
totalizing blindness
the technological and framing cannot let
quote what presences to come forth into
appearance
unquote and that which
presences appears as the very meaning of
human life
and thus castel implicitly enacts a
nihilism
hidden underneath the mania of
our technological advancements
another way of saying this is being
and meaning cannot be measured
quantified quantifiable or optimized
being is not a being and thus cannot be
gathered
as a resource of calculation
in other words gestel cannot respond
to nor hear the call of being or even
hear
being in its in the depth of the total
withdrawal
human beings however dwell in meaning
and is indwelled by
meaning as the very care which discloses
and beholds the world without
without a connection to what lets
presences
beat one's heart the suffering of human
life
is sure to become unbearable
the saving power dwells within the
violence
that the insidious nihilism
of our unframing epoch has on our soul
the saving power is disclosed precisely
in that we suffer in response to the
totalizing
takeover of castel that is i propose
the small but real presence
of the saving power as well as the
greatest
danger the fact that the human being
suffers in a world without meaning is
itself
meaningful and perhaps the last
possible sight where being can still
be heard in its place of hiddenness
and uh an ontologically attuned
listening to the primordial call of
being
in the post-modern epoch is attuning
precisely to beings withdrawal
more precisely it is hearing the
suffering of our souls
resulting from the hidden nihilism under
the technological progress of our time
perhaps listening to this suffering is
where the long concealed logos dwells
and who's listening gathers
within the gathering itself
and perhaps an original way of revealing
can come to sense from out of its own
concealment
as a gathering astonishment in
remembering
that this is
it is with this attuned listening that
we
now look into one of the forms of
suffering
this ontological withdrawal has taken
specifically in examining the nature of
sociality
and social discourse as it's being
restructured and transformed by
technology
this will set up the context in which to
look at
circling is a revealing response to the
framing of sociality in the post-modern
ebook
okay here's the next section the world
is social
in summary so far the first section we
considered the role of the logo
the world the logos plays in revealing
the world
and human life as implicitly meaningful
through examining some of the fragments
of heraclitus we saw that
it was through the logos that the
non-appearing wholeness
of being as heard as
heard as the atoning harmony of beings
this allowed us to consider that the
nihilism
of our of our epoch could be seen as a
kind of
deafening to logos and thus revealing
the possibility
of learning to listen to the logos is a
possible response
to nihilism in the second section
we looked at examining how we got here
by examining heidegger's account of the
history of metaphysics
as being as being the path of the
forgetfulness and abandonment
of the being of beings starting with the
pre-socratics and culminating as
our as our current ebook of the age of
technology
excuse me we ended that section showing
that the saving power
and grace may dwell in and through the
suffering
brought about from the loss of meaning
is
something that could not be reached by
techne
and thus could be a small opening to a
new way of reviewing
in this section i will attempt to show
the way the standing reserve is
literally taking over
social discourse via the internet and
literally transforming the structure of
human relationships
leading to a growing and chronic sense
of loneliness
alienation and pain in
in in pain and correlation with it
flush this out first by showing how the
meaning of the world unfolds and
manifests
as the being with others
in primordial care once we see that it's
the world itself that is at stake in our
social relations
it will give us the background to see
how circling
as a direct response to the problem
and opening to the beginning of perhaps
the freedom from it this
will open the way for the final section
on circling and dialectic
we have touched we have touched on in
the previous section
how an epoch's understanding of being is
what governs the meaningful disclosure
of
the world at every level
as an epochs core logoy of
intelligibility unfolds and
changes in the form of its culture
of its cultures unfolding it does
so in and through social discourse
discourse okay this is really important
okay discourse
is the way the logos gathers
and he pop an epoch's understanding of
being
and substantiates maintains and
distributes it
as the meaningful structure of the world
as such the connection between discourse
and the world is ontological and thus
co-determines and disclose each other
as the worlding of the world in other
words
analogically speaking the world is the
conversation
we live in and how and how we live
in it is in the form of the conversation
we are having about it rilka
beautifully exemplifies our paradoxical
relation
to the world poetically thus
here's the poem world
was in the face of the beloved
but suddenly it poured out and was gone
world is outside world
cannot be grasped why
didn't i from the from the full
beloved from the full
i'm sorry why didn't i
from the full beloved face
as i raise it to my lips why
didn't i drink world so
near i couldn't almost
taste it ah
i drank insatiably i drank
but i was filled up also
with too much world and drinking
i myself ran over
given the world is the world by virtue
of it being being the horizon of
intelligibility in which interworldly
beings
meaningfully come to appearance
i turn to the social sciences for
further understanding of how
this meaning how this meaning comes to
be through language and social discourse
captain we have a problem
social sciences implicitly sees
sociology
sociology its object of study
as a region or category of the world
operating out of a cartesian metaphysics
social science by default starts from
the assumption that his subject a human
subject
becomes social as a result of its social
activity
with other subjects accounting for and
giving rise to
the social world it studies
however this begs the question as to
how a human subject becomes
social in the first place without
already knowing how to perform
the social activity by which it becomes
social
and the same goes for the world how does
the world become social through this
activity without the world already being
the condition of possibility
for that social activity to appear in
the first place
let alone itself being at stake in those
encounters
this unsolvable paradox arises out of a
classical
cartesian category mistake which
attempts to explain and secure something
onto logical with the epistemological
philosophical thinking since descartes
in a very real sense
has been an attempt to resolve the
tensions of descartes thinking
however from within the same
metaphysical
onto theological basis
which in the end advanced
the very tensions it
the very tensions in the attempt
to resolve them
to bring to light the ontological
connection
between sociality and the world i will
need to
think outside of and beyond modernity
taking the lead from history in in
loosening the cartesian grip
i call on the thinking of martin
heidegger specifically his thinking from
being in time
which quite literally transformed all
philosophical thinking
since it was published
martin heidegger's groundbreaking
philosophical work
published in 1927 being in time
pierced through modernity's cartesian
dualism
and disclosed man not as a as a subject
but as the sign literally transf
translates to being there
in other words with heidegger's
groundbreaking
hermenetic phenomenological way of
thinking
the modernist spell broke of conceiving
individuals as as encapsulated thinking
subjects
alongside the world as its object
instead within its with an astonishing
depth of thinking the world had not seen
since socrates heidegger's thinking
showed that the being of human being
was already always a being in the world
world discloses as
man's concealment and in turn
man unconceals as worlds withdrawal
as alan and as alan watts poetically
said
we do not come into this world
we come out of it as leaves
from a tree as the ocean
waves the universe
peoples adding to watts poems
as the universe people's people
world us people's
world ontologically as da sign
in the mode of care translated from the
german source
from this deeper ontological perspective
it is in and through the
through primordial care that
the world addresses us as situation
and it is also in and through care that
the loros
gathers us as radically open
to this address
bringing this all together to be
the being in the world we are is to
already always
find ourselves in a situation towards
which
we are concerned fully responding
this ontological primordial care
is the condition of possibility for the
logos
to gather the moreness of inexhaustible
intelligibility
as our beholden of what is of of
ultimate concern that's from tillich
ultimate concern understanding
the human being and the world as
ontologically belonging together
through being in the world
sets the stage for a way of
understanding sociality
from within the ontological wholeness
and already always belonging to design
as being in the world and not
a separate region or result of design
structure
you know a quote heidegger here
heidegger names
this mitzen as being with others
and i quote him here as being in the
world
da sign is at the same time being with
each other
the aim here is to assert that
mostly we do not exist as single persons
that that others are also present rather
being with each other or might might
said
implies an ontological characteristic
of dye sign that is equipment primordial
with being in the world this
aspect of design persists even if no one
else is actually spoken to or perceived
so in other words miteson
being translates like the way that we're
being in the world
is that we're already always being with
others even when we're alone
right so in other words our being
is a being with in other words we're not
soul proprietorships
standing on a world we're already in the
world in a social context
and the world shows up in terms of that
context
right mice might sin
being with others might send
names how insofar as i am being in the
world
i am being in as
being with others therefore we do not
become
a social being through being in the
world socially
with other people instead sociality
is an ontological dimension of being as
such
say it again instead sociality
is an ontological dimension of being as
such
and this social dimension of being shows
itself in how the world enables our
social relations
nicole krensberg uh
knutson in the abstract of his paper
on heidegger and the problem of others
states
and i quote him
arguing that the world not only makes
the appearance of others possible
but also that the world is itself at
stake
in these encounters unquote
i opened the section proposing that that
the historical epochs understanding of
being unfolds
and maintains as the intelligibility of
the world
in and through social discourse by using
heidegger's thinking
from being in time i attempted to break
free of a cartesian dualism
to show that man in the world as a
ontological wholeness
and that sociality was a dimension of
this ontological wholeness that being
refers to
as much as heidegger refers to as might
sin
as being with others with this
understanding we can begin to appreciate
that social discourse
does not primarily result in a social
world
quote unquote but much more profoundly
reveals the sociality of the world
itself
in the social relations it enables
with this much more profound
understanding that the world
as such is at stake in and through
discourse
as an ontological dimension of the world
i will next
look at the internets impact on
on the structures of social discourse
in the light of our current post-modern
epoch
you're looking through looking at
the takeover of the standing reserve
i will attempt to show how the internet
is transforming the meaning of human
relationships
and the and the possibility this
opens up in our response to nihilism
okay it's the last section and it's
called right now it's i'm calling it
from seeing others to enframing others
in a matter of less than 20 years the
technological advancement of the
internet
has literally connected the entire globe
with each other
by eliminating in a certain sense time
and space at the level of communication
between one another
as i write technology has
already expanded this to the object
level
with 3d printing and advanced
advances have been made in the ability
to make the molecular substances
to print these objects
as standing reserve takes the practices
of social discourse of
in our social relations come to be seen
as a
cybernetic system of inputs and outputs
and exchange of information along a
circuit as this happens
people are seen as a node of one's
network
the value of the node is derived from
how
they are seen by other nodes in the
network
the person as a node standing in reserve
as a as a resource available as part of
the network
the more connections you have made
you have the more valuable you are as a
resource of the network
communication is reduced to
transactional information exchange
within the network
the better the network the more
efficient the transactions between
its connections the more inputs a mode
a node has the more valuable and
powerful that node's output
in other words people are progressively
seen as a means to an
end versus as an end themselves of
ultimate value
as martin martin buber states
i vow as an end in themselves
social media companies and frame each
user
as a quantifiable data collected by
predictive algorithms captured and
gathered
into standing reserve to be exploited
for data in service of greater
predictors for greater capture
as the algorithms track the object of
your attention
so it can predict and feed your
attention with those
objects more optimized for your
attention to capture it
and be captured by it this in turn
this this in turn is measured
calculated and refined over and over
again
into tighter reciprocal feedback loops
that loop in all of your contacts your
friends your credit cards your purchase
your your travel
and even your pulse
as the distance between a tension and
optimized
object collapses so does the difference
between a tension
and its object as such
the collapse of distance between
attention and technology can be seen
in how the internet has become the
medium
of in the structure and the structural
economy of exchange
on virtually every level of human
existence both personally
and societally in other words
the means of attention itself has become
in many ways
fashioned shaped and structured
by and in terms of technology
through our phones calendars reminders
etc
that in turn have structured the way
that we think
and conceive our world in every way in a
way that's
virtually no pun intended invisible
to us before the internet's form of
texting messaging
um posting emailing etc the more basic
um the most basic mutual two-way
exchange of information
between two or more individuals always
had to take place
interpersonally through embodied social
discourse
and synchronistic communication in other
words
before the internet if you needed to
exchange the most basic information
you had to do it in person or at least
over the telephone
in other words communication required
commuting the internet made it possible
to exchange information
uncoupled from live in-person speech
in other words it became possible to
connect without having to relate
this is no small change especially when
one considers that human beings become
who they are
in and through these very living
relations
which last through one's entire lifetime
a child develops in and through the
living relations
with the parent and immediate family
mature in these relations mature them to
be capable
of expanding into their relations with
their peers
and teachers in school through which
the child matures and transforms
into a responsible adult this
change is a transformation predicated on
the individual
no longer being dependent on the
previous relationships
and by virtue of it
by virtue of it comes into greater
relationship
with society this greater relationship
with society in turn becomes the next
relational context which a person
develops and transforms through
okay so this i haven't quite worked the
work this is going to be a little bit
jumpy here because i'm i'm just trying
to rework this so i don't know if this
will make sense
um this experience so how exactly do
human beings paradoxically become
differentiated individuals through
relationship with others
human relationship is a is the place
where the two most basic existential
drives a human being has
is brought forward into living tension
in other words to be a human being is to
is is to
deeply desire and be driven
for the security that comes from
a sense of belonging a belonging to
tribe to commit
into community at the same time and on
the other hand
is the existential drive to stand out
as a unique individual glowing and
cosmic
significance it is in and through
our interpersonal face-to-face
relationships throughout our entire
lifetime
that embody both the challenges
and possibilities for these drives to be
fulfilled or stunted
in person face-to-face relations
call on these deepest capacities of body
mind and awareness into exercise
so in other words what i'm trying to get
at is this this sense of like it's it's
in
dialogue right it's in it's in in the
most basic conversation
where i'm on one line i'm called into we
right i'm called into belonging and
inhabiting
and belonging with you but to the degree
that i can belong
truthfully right and and contribute to
that belonging
right it's to the degree that i can also
be an individual that stands
out in that contribution right and so
ideally right human maturity it's always
about this sense of relationship
that feeds back and i'm fed back into in
such a way that my contributions reveal
my individuality
that reveal what i'm contributing to
that disclose myself as an individual
that discloses the community and if this
auto poetic sense works out
you end up becoming a pretty cool person
right
so but but like that's at every level
like in every
but in where that culminates you'll
almost say the literal and the symbolic
culmination
or theater of that enactment of those
two existential drives
is relationship is human relationship
the living relationship so basically
what i'm getting at is like
what happens right where
technology all of a sudden introduces
this division
right where i have all these ways and
and we're going more and more this
direction where
all of a sudden the structure of reality
even if this just happened a little bit
right you could just imagine this like
where all of a sudden the word is not
happening just a little bit it's
happening a lot where the structure of
reality all of a sudden
no longer requires these relations
or at least makes them optional
and by the way those i don't know if
you've noticed but those relationships
are a pain
in the ass right so
there's nothing comfortable about them
um in fact real ones are really
uncomfortable a lot of times that's what
makes them real
so but now that we have an option it's
built into the structure of reality in a
way that it wasn't before
what's the impact of that and that's
what i'm kind of going into
and so i'll go into that more and then
i'm going to go into laying up circling
and how what circling is which is the
practice of in relationship being with
what is
and start to distinguish this as a
response to nihilism but also leading
into
um dialectic philosophical dialectic
into the ground of being able to
to directly deal with the structure of
reality in discourse
right what that means and how circling's
revealing this so
thank you for hanging in there if you've
had if you hung in there this long
i've i've really appreciated the
opportunity just to
walk through this i think when i come
back to this and start writing again i'm
going to
do so with much more of a grip on what
i'm saying
or what wants to be said thank you